<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

	<properties>
		<title>JIAC MAS's External Interfaces</title>
		<author email="jiactng-dev@dai-labor.de">JIAC TNG team</author>
	</properties>

	<body>
		<section name="JIAC MAS's External Interfaces">
			<p>This chapter gives a brief overview of external interfaces offered
				or required by an executed JIAC MAS (multi-agent system). External
				interface in this context means, the interface is published and can
				be seen from outside of a JIAC MAS that is executed. JIAC
				framework's published API, which is used mainly for implementation
				work during development, is not focus of this article. Other
				articles in this Maven sites of the JIAC project will give an even
				deeper insight into JIAC's components and its interfaces and how to
				use them.
			</p>
			<p>Why is it important to know about a JIAC MAS's external
				interfaces?
			</p>
			<ul>
				<li>As for all software components and applications, knowledge of
					interfaces (and thus of possible inputs and outputs) is a necessary
					prerequisite to use a software as well as for further development
					and maintenance.
				</li>
				<li>JIAC framework and tools are open source. You are free to use
					and modify JIAC for your purposes.
				</li>
				<li>JIAC's framework is component based and extensible by individual
					components (AgentNodeBeans and AgentBeans), which can realize
					individual defined external interfaces (provided or required
					interfaces).
				</li>
				<li>A MAS is embedded into an environment. Agents need to interact
					or communicate with their environment, for this they can have
					sensors and effectors, which technically also comprise interfaces.
				</li>
				<li>Agents in a multi-agent system usually communicate with each
					other, e.g. for coordination and interoperation reasons. This
					communication is pass through interfaces.
				</li>
				<li>A JIAC MAS can be deployed as a distributed system, which makes
					a communication through interfaces necessary.
				</li>
				<li>Sending information over an insecure channel raises the wish to
					protect communication and access to interfaces.
				</li>
				<li>Monitoring and managing a MAS requires interfaces.</li>
				<li>Maybe you will come up with more important aspects ...</li>
			</ul>

			<subsection name="Overvivew">
				<p>		         
					<a href="images/External-Interfaces.png">
						<img src="images/External-Interfaces.png" alt="JIAC MAS's External Interfaces"/>
					</a>
				</p>
				
				<p>This UML component analysis diagram depicts a JIAC AgentNode's
					external interfaces that are used during execution. A JIAC MAS is
					composed of one or many of those AgentNodes. In the diagram,
					representing a single AgentNode, these external interfaces are
					represented by provided and required interface UML notations
					protruding over the system boundary. Furthermore, this diagram
					should be interpreted as analysis diagram, outlining the concepts
					of JIAC's interfaces. Consequentially, classes and components
					realizing the depicted components and interfaces in the source code
					could be named differently. Of course a JIAC AgentNode is composed
					of more components than illustrated in this diagram; this diagram
					focuses on the external interfaces. Apart from that, some
					components in this diagram don't have any external interfaces, but
					they are still part of the diagram to support further explanations.
				</p>
				<p>Important note: It depends on a JIAC MAS's individual
					configuration of what components the MAS is composed of. Thus, a
					JIAC MAS can have a different number and types of external
					interfaces. But if you are using the predefined Spring-based
					configurations (e.g., SimpleAgent, NodeWithDirectory, NodeWithJMX)
					your JIAC MAS will have all or a subset of the depicted external
					interfaces, or a superset when using individual components.
				</p>
				<p>The concepts of the depicted components and interfaces are
					described below. If you want to learn more about a certain
					component or functionality and know how to use them, we recommend
					you to dive into a particular chapter of this JIAC documentation
					describing this component or functionality. Please note that each
					JIAC project (e.g. jiactng, agentCore and agentCoreAPI) has its own
					documentation.
				</p>
			</subsection>

			<subsection
				name="AgentBeans, AgentNodeBeans and Other Individual Components">
				<p>Adding individual or predefined (by the JIAC developing team or
					by third-party-providers) components to a JIAC MAS is a easy and
					common way to extend the behaviour of a JIAC MAS. To plug in
					components is easy because of the component-based architecture of
					the JIAC framework. Adding AgentBeans and AgentNodeBeans is the
					intended way to extend the behaviour of Agents and AgentNodes.
					Configuration is usually done via a Spring-based agent
					configuration XML file. However, the current implementation (JIAC
					5.2.1) doesn't provide the functionality to plug in components,
					e.g. AgentBeans, during runtime via external interfaces, even this
					would be technically possible. Thus, the bean plug-in mechanism is
					not covered by this article – currently it's more an functionality
					provided by an API used in the implementation phase.
				</p>
				<p>But these individual or predefined components may use, but are
					not obliged to provide external interfaces. Individual components
					also can use JIAC's internal services, e.g., an AgentBean usually
					uses the CommunicationBean (which internally provides access to the
					MessageBroker) to send messages to other Agents.
				</p>
				<p>AgentBeans can provide services (aka. actions), accessible by
					other JIAC components (e.g. Agents) and external clients. As any
					other individual component, an AgentBean is free to provide own
					external interfaces to access these services (usually for non-JIAC
					components). However, JIAC implements a build-in mechanism that
					makes it possible to publish and access services with the help of
					the Directory (it holds information about other Agents and their
					services on the local AgentNode, and globally in the platform) and
					the MessageBroker; this scenario, using the Directory and
					MessageBroker to publish services is mainly for using services by
					other JIAC components, rather than by external clients. That's why
					many AgentBeans that provides actions don't have own external
					interfaces.
				</p>
				<p>Because the existence and nature of external interfaces that are
					provided or required by individual components (including AgentBeans
					and AgentNodeBeans) depends on the developers implementation, there
					is nothing more to say about the interfaces of individual
					components.
				</p>
			</subsection>

			<subsection name="MessageBroker">
				<p>An AgentNode can be equipped with a MessageBroker (which is
					technically an AgentNodeBean). The MessageBroker supplies messaging
					between JIAC components via a message bus. It can be used e.g. for
					inter-Agent communication between Agents located either on the same
					AgentNode or on other AgentNodes. And the Directory component needs
					the MessageBroker to connect to external Directories for
					synchronizing its entries. The CommunicationBean provides access to
					the message bus.
				</p>
				<p>Configuration of the MessageBroker (as for other JIAC components)
					is done with the agent configuration file. The predefined JIAC
					Agent configurations NodeWithDirectory and its specializations
					NodeWithJMX, NodeWithSecuredJMX and NodeWithRegistry already comes
					with a MessageBroker realized with ActiveMQ. Whereas the
					CommunicationBean already comes with the predefined configuration
					SimpleAgent. So, usually your JIAC MAS will have a MessageBroker
					and a CommunicationBean as depicted in the UML diagram. This
					predefined MessageBroker provides an external interface for
					receiving messages that are send on the message bus and it requires
					an interface (e.g. a network interface) for sending messages on the
					message bus. These interfaces are part of ActiveMQ. Messages are
					addressed by a so called transport URI.
				</p>
				<p>The predefined MessageBroker also provides several discovery
					mechanisms. The intention of a discovery mechanism is, that
					communication partners (e.g. Agents) residing on different
					AgentNodes and maybe on different computers will find each other
					automatically to be able to communicate. In JIAC 5.2.1 two
					discovery mechanisms are implemented:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Multicast discovery messages.</li>
					<li>Discovery via gateways.</li>
				</ul>
				<p>Multicast discovery messages, containing the transport URI, are
					send periodically over a predefined multicast socket for discovery.
					The predefined discovery URI is
					smartmulticast://default?group=jiac-tng. ActiveMQ-Broker will build
					a network-of-brokers with other brokers within the network (due to
					technical limitations of multicast messages usually this means
					inside an IP subnet) that are sharing the same logical discovery
					multicast-address. This is what is called in JIAC a Platform.
				</p>
				<p>Discovery via gateways is used for scenarios where multicast
					discovery doesn't work:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>If communication partners (or MessageBroker) are in different
						subnets.
					</li>
					<li>If certain network nodes (e.g. routers) doesn't support
						multicast properly.
					</li>
				</ul>
				<p>In cases multicast is not working, several MessageBrokers can be
					connected via Gateways. A Gateway can be realized with an AgentNode
					using a ActiveMQBroker configured as Gateway. The intention of
					using gateways is similar to the intention of using a RMI registry,
					which is used if the JMX multicast discovery mechanism of the JMX
					management interface is not working.
				</p>
				<p>Both discovery mechanisms can be combined in order to link
					different network-of-brokers to one large network-of-brokers
					connected by gateways, which also becomes handy for discovering
					remote services.
				</p>
				<p>By default messages send by the MessageBroker are not encrypted
					and the interface doesn't use authentication. JIAC provides a way
					to secure the MessageBroker's transport channel with SSL/TLS using
					certificates. Technically, the protocol of the
					ActiveMQTransportConnector's transport URI is set from TCP to SSL.
					The multicast discovery is not protected by SSL/TLS, because the
					multicast messages just carry the transport URI as payload.
				</p>
			</subsection>

			<subsection name="Management Interface">
				<p>JIAC's Management Interface component is realized with JMX and
					allows remote (but also local) management and monitoring of
					manageable JIAC components via a JMX interface. The predefined JIAC
					configuration NodeWithDirectory doesn't have the Management
					Interface activated, but NodeWithJMX, NodeWithSecuredJMX and
					NodeWithRegistry do have (by providing a RMI JMX connector).
				</p>
				<p>An activated Management Interface component establishes a
					management channel. This comprises multicast discovery mechanisms
					and the JMX management interface accessible (remote or local) over
					RMI.
				</p>
				<p>The Management Interface provides two discovery mechanisms
					(similar to the MessageBroker component):
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Multicast discovery messages (UDP datagrams).</li>
					<li>Discovery via RMI Registry.</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					The multicast discovery messages (datagram packages via UPD) are
					sent periodically over a multicast socket using the default
					discovery URI multicast://226.6.6.7:9999. The datagrams contains a
					JMX RMI URI (service:jmx:rmi://
					&lt;IP&gt;
					/
					&lt;path&gt;) which is necessary to connect successfully to a certain
					Management Interface component (technically to a RMI connector
					server). Sending multicast discovery messages containing the JMX
					RMI URI is an own implementation and not provided by JMX.
				</p>
				<p>The RMI registry is realized with ja Java tool of the same name.
					Note: By default the RMI registry has to be on the same computer
					where the MBean server is executed within the JVM. But the
					management client that is using the RMI registry (e.g.
					JMXManagementClient or ASGARD) is allowed to be on a remote
					computer.
				</p>
				<p>The Management Interface provides an external interface following
					the pull (a command-query-interface) and push (by inversion of
					control with observers) technique. This interface is implemented
					using standard JMX technology.
				</p>
				<p>Which JIAC components are manageable when JMX is activated? Every
					class (or component) implementing ILifecycle also implements the
					interface Manageable, this are: Agent, AgentBean, AgentNode,
					AgentNodeBean, Memory, ExecutionCycle. These components and
					specialisation are manageable. But all these manageable components
					of a JIAC MAS are accessed in a centralized way through their
					related AgentNode.
				</p>
				<p>Technically JMX realizes the access to manageable components via
					RMI with so-called RMI connector servers, which enables management
					clients like JConsole to manage and monitor the MBeans remotely
					over a network. In JIAC, only an AgentNode has JMX connector
					servers. An AgentNode can have multiple JMX connector server, one
					for a combination of a protocol (e.g. RMI, HTTP/SOAP – but
					currently JIAC is using just RMI) and for a network interface (e.g.
					wlan0, eth0). During an AgentNode's runtime these connector servers
					are created or deleted, e.g., depending of available network
					interfaces on the host computer. Thus, only an AgentNode is sending
					periodically multicast discovery messages, each of them containing
					the JMX RMI URI of one of the many JMX connector servers an
					AgentNodes possesses.
				</p>
				<p>By default, the communication is not encrypted and the interface
					doesn't use authentication. SSL/TLS can be activated to secure the
					transport. Multicast discovery messages are not secured with
					SSL/TLS, because they just contain a JMX RMI URI. Furthermore the
					JMX management interface can be secured by using authentication
					with a user name and password.
				</p>
				<p>JIAC provides the library JMXManagementClient that provides a
					convenient Java API for managing and monitoring a JIAC MAS with
					activated JMX Management Interface. For instance the management and
					monitoring application ASGARD is using this library.
				</p>


			</subsection>

		</section>
	</body>
</document>
