<document xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.cs.tu-berlin.de/%7Esmarqoo/maven-changes.xsd">
	<properties>
		<title>Changes</title>
		<author email="axle.hessler@dai-labor.de">axle</author>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<release version="5.0.5" date="2009-12-03" description="Minor release">
			<action dev="jakob" type="add">
				ASGARD - JIAC V Agent Platform Monitor - 3D!
			</action>
			<action dev="kaisers" type="add">
				AgentUnit - Unit testing of JIAC V agent services made easier.
			</action>
			<action dev="kaisers" type="add">
				Deployment of JADL scripts now uses load distribution.
			</action>
			<action dev="kaisers" type="update">
				Load measurement more robust.
			</action>
			<action dev="kaisers" type="update">
				Load distribution during starttime.
			</action>
			<action dev="burkhardt" type="update">
				JADL++ improved!!: based on Eclipse TMF v0.7.1; services published in IDirectory;
				new headers (import, include, mapping, define); new modifier for numeric datatypes;
				new events (message, time); new control flow (switch-case); new commands (listen, receive, send).
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="5.0.4" date="2009-01-27" description="Minor release">
			<action dev="loeffelholz" type="add">
				Integration of IRML user management as basic service module with flexible user agent authentication
				and authorisation of JIAC actions.
			</action>
			<action dev="marcel" type="add">
				A gateway for reliable host name resolution for agent discovery and inter-agent communication.
			</action>
			<action dev="burkhardt" type="add">
				OWL support in JADL++ interpreter and service matcher.
			</action>
			<action dev="masuch" type="add">
				A service matcher matching OWL-S service descriptions.
			</action>
			<action dev="burkhardt" type="update">
				Improvement of JADL++ interpreter.
			</action>
			<action dev="kuester" type="update">
				Rule engine API and Drools support has been extracted from JIAC and established as own independent module
				for use in other DAI-Labor projects without JIAC. Integration of ruleengine into JIAC agents is now build on
				top of it.
			</action>
			<action dev="keiser" type="update">
				Enhanced execution cycle now supports parallel action execution.
			</action>
			<action type="fix">
				Services are now reliably discovered if they are there, also cross-node.
			</action>
			<action dev="moekon" type="fix">
				SessionIds are now passed down to sub-services during service usage.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="5.0.3" date="2008-07-07" description="Minor release">
		</release>
		<release version="5.0.1" date="2007-11-08" description="First release">
			<action dev="axle" type="add">
				Additionally to the normal source and test code structure
				a site will be created which provides basic information about the module on the one
				hand, and information about the quality of the module on the other.
			</action>
			<action dev="axle" type="add">
				You may now log your changes in a ChangeLog using
				this changes.xml. A report will be generated automatically and integrated
				in the site.
			</action>
			<action dev="joachim" type="add">
				Strict mode support added to "de.dailab.jiactng.agentcore.lifecycle.DefaultLifecycleHandler".
			</action>
		</release>
	</body>
</document>
